### M. Susan Schmidt, PhD

Beaufort, NC USA, (252) 269-0032

susu@susanschmidt.net, <a href="mailto:susanschmidt.net">susu@susanschmidt.net</a>, <a href="mailto:susanschmidt.net">susanschmidt.net</a> <a href="mailto:susanschmidt.net">Editorial Freelancers Association <a href="mailto:http://www.the-efa.org/dir/memberinfo.php?mid=11449">http://www.the-efa.org/dir/memberinfo.php?mid=11449</a> >

# Developmental Editor, Author, Publisher, Workshop Leader

I am listed among Top Ten Editors in New England (though I live on NC coast); UMass, MIT, & Harvard recommend me to faculty and doctoral students. I am an Author, Editor, and Educator with 30+ years experience as college and secondary teacher of literature, creative and technical writing; science policy, decision-making, and ethics; and 20 years as government editor and science analyst. Worldwide I edit books; I started Kakapo Press; I lead Beaufort Writing Group. I row, sail, swim, practice yoga, walk my Boykin spaniel, call contra dances, play bass fiddle, as Master Gardener build community gardens, clerk Quaker Meeting, and convene Carteret Crossroads (conservation group). I just renewed my US Coast Guard Captain's license the seventh time (34 years). As naturalist, I travel to witness natural diversity. For my next book, I am walking Celtic coastal paths warmed by the Gulf Stream. Won 2012 Guy Owen Poetry Prize, 2016 Applewhite finalist. Poem in *Literary Trails of Eastern NC*. My books are *Song of Moving Water* (novel), *Salt Runs in My Blood* (poetry), and *Landfall Along the Chesapeake* (nonfiction boat adventure).

### **Work History**

# Developmental Editor, Beaufort Writing Group, Beaufort, NC

January 2009 to Present

I advise authors on narrative structure; copyedit grammar and style. Edit novels, memoirs; academic/scientific journal articles, polish dissertations. Agent of my client says, "This is the sharpest improvement I've ever seen, from 1st draft to the 2nd." I edited *Beach Book, Science of the Shore* (Columbia UP); *Connecting the Drops* (Cornell UP,); *Constructing Ecologies* (Routledge, 2017); UN Pacific Climate Change book. Copyeditor: Harvard Business School's *Business History Review*. Edited 25 novels, including *Song of the Mokihana*, 1917 Pacific schooner novel; *Light on Water*, New Zealand Maori saga.

### **University Professor and Secondary Teacher**

1973 to 2009

I taught university technical and creative writing, American literature, creative nonfiction, environmental literature & philosophy, science communication, conflict resolution, environmental policy & community planning at Hampton University 2007, Brevard College 1996–2001, Warren Wilson College 1994–95, NC School of Science & Math 1989–94, Duke University 1989–93, College of Charleston 1987–88, NC State University 1983, University of Virginia Engineering School 1979, Carteret Community College 2001–2008 & 1979–83. Taught secondary literature, journalism, French, global environmental issues at SC Governor's School 1988; Andover 1989 & 1969, Collegiate School in Richmond, VA, 1973–76. Fellow at NEH Environmental Imagination Institute at Vassar, National Humanities Center, NC Center for Advancement of Teaching, Duke University Environment, Natural Resources Leadership Institute.

#### **Curriculum Designer, Grant-Writer, Fellowships**

1976 to 2010

I wrote research and land-acquisition (for Nature Conservancy) grants topping \$10 million. Designed curriculum for NC State University on humanities for engineering students, Duke University on environmental philosophy, Medical University of South Carolina on AIDS Education and Medical Ethics for Family Doctors, Stratford Hall on environmental history, Christchurch School on environmental Chesapeake studies, Brevard College and NC School of Science & Math on environmental humanities. Received grants from American Association of University Women on Southern Appalachian native plants & traditional music, National Endowment for the Humanities to design environmental-humanities curriculum, National Science Foundation on interbasin water-transfer, Environmental Protection Agency on nonpoint-source-pollution runoff control, Office of Education for land-use/ water-quality workshops, Fulbright Foundation to teach English in West Germany. Creative-writing fellowships: VA Center for Creative Arts in VA 2000 and SW France 2008, Vermont Studio Center for fiction workshop 2006, Environmental Writing Workshop/ Montana 2000, Bread Loaf for nonfiction workshop 1999, Hambidge Center/ Georgia 1999; NC Arts Council to research Captain John Smith and Jamestown 2002.

# **Contract Technical Editor & Workshop Trainer**

1996 to 2008

USDA Forest Service, Southern Research Station, Asheville, NC, and Atlanta, GA

I edited scientists' articles and books, including *Southern Appalachian Assessment; Deerskins And Cotton, Savannah River Site before 1950; Ecology and Management, 50 Years on Savannah River Site.* Led workshops (grammar, style, logic, & law) training endangered-species biologists to write legally-defensible environmental-assessment documents. Led grant-writing workshops for federal scientists.

### **Environmental Scientist/ Policy Analyst/ Editor/ Mediator**

1977 to 2001

For NC Natural Resources Leadership Institute I mediated between NC Forest Resources & Natural Heritage to protect natural areas and wrote recreational-management plan for 12,000-acre DuPont State Forest. Mediated for Transylvania Dispute Settlement Center, Brevard, NC. Edited Environmental Science Dictionary, Bruccoli Clark. As Virginia Sea Grant Editor, VIMS, College of William & Mary, edited two monthly newsletters on commercial fishing and marine-science research. Edited San Diego Log (waterfront newspaper). As Environmental Scientist for NC Coastal Management, Morehead City, wrote policy reports and testified to Coastal Resources Commission on land use regulations to protect estuarine water quality, including wetland mitigation, coal ports, oil refineries; wrote grant proposal and management plan to establish NC Estuarine Research Reserve. For Nature Conservancy as steward, wrote Carrot Island Preserve Management Plan, Beaufort, NC; wrote acquisition grant and management plan for Ivy Creek Natural Area, Charlottesville, VA. For US Department of Interior, Washington, reviewed environmental-impact statements on dams, mediated among departments to write Secretary's letter.

### **Education**

Conflict-Resolution Fellow, Natural Resources Leadership Institute, NC State University, 1998–2000 Bioethics, Environmental Philosophy Fellow, Duke University Divinity School, 1990–93 PhD, American Literature, University of South Carolina, 1990

MA, Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 1980 Watershed ecology, water quality planning
Botany study, Highlands (UNC), 1996, Mt. Lake (UVa) biology stations, 1976, 1990
MA, English, University of Virginia, 1972; Teaching License in English, Science, French, Reading
BA, English; French, German, Connecticut College, May 1971; Oxford University, England, Honors 1969–70

# **Publications**

I am author of *Salt Runs in My Blood* (poetry) and *Song of Moving Water* (novel) (Kakapo Press, February 2015); *Landfall Along the Chesapeake, in the Wake of Captain John Smith* (Johns Hopkins UP, 2006). I published 14 poems (*Southern Poetry Review, Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina, Kakalak, ISLE, Tar River Review, Land Report, NC Literary Review*), 6 book chapters, 7 literary essays (*Shenandoah, Milkweed*), 10 journal articles, 150 magazine/ newspaper articles. I edited 35 technical books, science reports & proceedings, 26 dissertations and journal articles, 25 novels & 20 memoirs.

# **Selected Honors & Fellowships**

2016 James Applewhite finalist; 2012 Owen Poetry Prize, Poem in *Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina* VA Center for Creative Arts Fellowship SW France & VA; NC Arts Council grant Vermont Studio Center, Bread Loaf, Robert Ruark Fiction Award, NC Writers Blumenthal Reader Montana's Environmental Writing Program; Orion's Fire & Grit, Ossabaw Southern Nature Writers National Endowment for Humanities 2 Fellowships, AAUW, NSF, Fulbright

**Member**: Editorial Freelancers Association < <a href="http://www.the-efa.org/dir/memberinfo.php?mid=11449">http://www.the-efa.org/dir/memberinfo.php?mid=11449</a> Association for Study of Literature & Environment, National Association of Science Writers, Master Gardeners, Association of Writing Programs. Boards: Local Food Network, Junior Sailing.

**Recent Travel:** Brittany, Guernsey, Somerset, Wales, Scottish Highlands, Ireland, Cornwall Coastal Path, Camino de Santiago, Kenya/ Ecuador/ Costa Rica Bird Surveys; New Zealand. Kayaked 500 miles NC/SC 1999, Alaska Prince William Sound 1983. Delivered sailboats to West Indies 1980s. Next: Belize, Iceland.